um so this is a CH
121 thus have I
heard on one occasion the blessed one
was living at
saath at the place of meara's mother
then in the evening having emerged from
seclusion the venerable Ananda
approached the blessed one having
approached the blessed one having PID
respects he sat down to one side sitting
down in what side the venerable Ananda
said to this blessed
one there was this one occasion when
blessed one was living among the sakan
is sakan town called nagar
raka there bante in the presence of the
blessed one this was heard by me now
Ananda I often dwell dwell with a place
of emptiness
so I'm not sure B if this was well heard
well grasped well attended well
remembered by me certainly Anand this
was well heard well grasp well attended
well remembered by you both before and
now I often dwell with the place of
emptiness Ananda just as this place of
meara's mother is empty of elephants
cattle and mares empty of gold and
silver empty of crowds of women men
there is this non-emptiness
namely the Oneness dependent on the
banga so the point
here is
um the presence of the
negative uh and by that mean that that's
that's basically what emptiness means
presence of emptiness is presence of
certain absences so in this particular
case uh the the the migara's mother
Palace is empty it's absent of elephants
cattle Mayors gold silver crowds women
men but what is not empty of is a group
of the
banga so attending to to that which is
absent as a as a uniform basis can be
can be um can be seen as a as a as a
uniform phenomena as a single phenomena
that's that's what it's meant by uh
Oneness basically one
pointedness the mind is is established a
on a single more General phenomena in
this case the negative phenomena of
absence so the Oneness dependent on the
banga in just this way Ananda piku not
attending to the perception of
Village not attending to the perception
of
people attends to the Oneness dependent
on the perception of the
forest so aiku can
surmount the perception of the village
perception of people by having his mind
established on the perception of the
forest which means even when he's not in
the forest he could maintain that
forest he could maintain that
perception so although that perception
will be absent when he is among people
or in the village his mind still remain
established upon that Oneness
and that's what it says here his mind
jumps onto it is clear about remains
with inclined towards the perception of
the forest so it's not some sort of a
like a a mystical nimita or whatever you
want to call it upon which his
perception is established it's actually
the clarity of the of the of the peripheral
clarity of the of the of the peripheral
awareness of his
experience while he was in the forest
Still Remains present because his mind
is established upon it even when he
comes out of the forest so he uses the
perceptions of the
forest he uses the perceptions of the
forest to to maintain his mind
established upon their Oneness even when
he leaves the
forest so he understands thus Whatever
anxiety there might be dependent on the
perception of the village those are not
present here because his mind refuses to
descend from the more General perception
of the the mood of the forest that he
dwells in refus to descends onto the the
perceptions of the village so so so he
never gets um pulled by them which means
any anxiety that can arise on account of
the Perceptions in the in the village
does not bother him
Whatever anxiety there might be
dependent on the perception of people
those anxieties are not present here
there is only this much anxiety this
much disturbance namely based upon the
Oneness dependent on the perception of
the forest so if something were to happen to
forest so if something were to happen to
that Forest he's still liable to a
certain um amount of disturbance some
certain amount of discomfort arising on
account of it because that's where his
mind is
established he understands having
arrived at this perception it is empty
of the perception of the village having
of the perception of people there is
only this non-emptiness the Oneness
dependent on the perception of the
forest that is not empty but he dwells
empty of perceptions of of people in the
village so so it can be seen here it's
not it's not some sort of mystical
emptiness mystical reality behind the
appearances it's it's a it's a it's a presence of
it's it's a it's a it's a presence of
absence in this case absence of um UNH
wholesome environment or environment
that's less conducive for practice
absence of people absence of the village
so even when when the monk goes for
pinap goes back into the village he he
his mind can still remain established
upon the absence of the village as in he
still rooted in his presence in the
forest and that's what it say says here
he says he has
understood the the um the emptiness of
the perception of the village and The
Emptiness of the perception of the
people and the non-emptiness that is
present is the the um the Oneness that's
dependent upon the perceptions of the
forest thus on on account of whatever
it's not there the absence I've been
talking about he sees it as it empty and
whatever remains he understands it as
this is present so even when he's in the
village the perceptions of the forest
are present for him because that's where
his mind is
established so the particular perception
of the village that he has they do not
reach they do not change the background
of his mood of that peripheral
mindfulness and awareness which is still
rooted in the perceptions of the forest
and that's how he's not disturbed by
anything that he sees in the village or
hears in the village
and then it says and in this wayanda
there is this authentic undistorted
clear entry into the
emptiness furthermore Ananda abiku not
attending to the perception of the
village not attending to the perception
of people not attending to the
perception of the forest attends to the
Oneness dependent on the perception of
the earth so he goes even higher after
after his mind has been established upon
the perception of the forest he realizes
that he can still be disturbed on the
account of
that he he realized that he can still be
disturbed on account of it so then he
goes further but in this Cas he this
case he doesn't actually go anywhere he
discerns what is even more
General in the perception of the village
in the perception of the people in the
per of the forest it's the perception of
the solidity of the phenomena the the
the aspect the element of Earth which
means it's the most General presence of
phenomena which doesn't really require
you to be in any particular
place uh but but simply to discern the
uh the aspect of of solidity the aspect
of resistance of things that appear
through your
senses um
and and the reason why this is why why
the mind can get established upon this
is because anything solid in the world
anything uh any any any environment that
you that that um that you live in
already partakes in the environment of
Earth as a
whole um the the forest the mountain the
the the island the continent Earth as a
whole the element of Earth is there
present all the way down into into the
most particular aspects of some
particular Village of such and such name
with such and such
people so his mind then clarifies and
discerns that phenomenon of earth that
is that is contained in all the more
particular perceptions of the forest of
the village of the people so his mind
jumps onto is clear about remains with
inclines towards the perception of Earth
Anand just is a bullhide well stretched
by 100 Stakes is free from folds in just
this wayand aiku not attending to all
these up and down slopes in the earth
rivers and Creek stumps thorns and
sticks uneven mountain rock attends to
the Oneness dependent of the perception
of Earth so through the element of Earth
he discerns the actual
Earth and uh that Earth is equally
present in anything else that appears on
that Earth so there he doesn't he's not
bothered by any uh Mountains for
different environments jumps and
everything is stretched and even in
terms of its presence in terms of his
his uh um mind being established upon
the Oneness dependent upon the
perception of
Earth he understands thus Whatever
anxiety there might be dependent on the
perception of people those are not
present here Whatever anxiety there
might be dependent on the perception of
forest those are not present here there
is only this much anxiety namely the
Oneness dependent on the perception of
Earth he stands having arrived at this
perception it is empty of the perception
of people having arrived at this
of the forest there is only this
non-emptiness namely the one is
dependent on the perception of Earth so
by establishing his
mind upon the most General perception of
Earth as a
whole he is thus empty of all the other
perceptions
thus on account of whatever it's not
there he sees it as empty and whatever
remains he understands it is this is
present and in this way Ananda there is
this authentic undistorted clear entry
into
emptiness so then it goes further
following the same principle going for
the next even higher establish M of mind
which is still based upon the the
perception on the level of the
peripheral mindfulness and that is uh
the perception of the domain of the
Infinite Space
again even the element of Earth even
even the solidity aspect of things that
appear already requires a negative
phenomenon of space space is discerned
through that appearance which means
space is always there whenever there is
appearance sh quiet boy
appearance which means that space can
also be discerned as that which is in
common to absolutely everything that has
a nature to appear and that's why it's
called the Infinite
Space so his
mind develops clarity about inclines
towards that perception of the domain of
the Infinite Space it actually properly
discerns it within things that are
present he understands thus Whatever
anxiety there might be dependent on the
perception of the forest dependent on
the perception of Earth those are not
present here there is only this much
anxiety the Oneness dependent on the
perception of the domain of Infinite
Space and then he understands that
having arrived at this perception it is
empty of the perception of forest rather
this perception empty of the perception
of Earth there is is the non-emptiness
the perception of the domain of the
Infinite
Space then he goes further not attending
to the perception of Earth not attending
to the perception domain of Infinite
Space he then attends to even
greater General phenomenon even even
even more peripheral even more subtle
even more
fundamental and uh that is simply
Consciousness as we mentioned in other
talks Consciousness means presence of
phenomena presence of things the the
aspect of presence is what Consciousness
is usually people think Consciousness is
in them and because of that they think
things appear for them but that's not
the case Consciousness is out there with
the phenomenon
peripherally you can't attend the
Consciousness but you can learn how to
non-directly attend the peripheral nature of whatever
attend the peripheral nature of whatever
it's present and by doing so that's how
you develop emptiness of what's what's
in front of you as we just read through
this suta so by not attending to the
perception of the forest that the Monk
Is In by not attending to the perception
of the earth that the forest is in that
the Monk Is In by not attending to the
perception of the Infinite Space that
the Earth is in that the forest is in
that the Monk Is in he attends to the
perception of the just
plain simple presence it doesn't matter
what is present how big it is big or
small far or near presence is there
that's all that he discerns peripherally
that's all that he that he becomes clear
about and his mind gets established upon
and that's what means the Infinity of
Consciousness the infinite Consciousness
as in the presence Discerning its nature
not bound to the any particular
manifestation of it again it's not a
mystification is just a simple
structural uh discernment in regard to
things that are
present so by emptying himself of the
perceptions of himself of the
perceptions of um of the banga of the
perceptions of the forest of the
perceptions of the earth of the
perceptions of the Infinite Space
Infinite Space yes uh he then arrives
at the perceptions of the infinite
Consciousness he understands what
whatever disturbance they might be
dependent on perception of Earth
perception of Infinite Space it's not
present here only the disturbance
dependent on the perception of
Consciousness then he goes even further
surmounting Infinite
Space surmounting the infinite
Consciousness attends the perception of
the nothingness and nothingness is the
negative in regard to the that very very
general and subtle Consciousness so once
the the perceptions of Forest the the
perceptions of oneself the perceptions
of the forest the perceptions of Earth
the perceptions of Infinite Space the
perceptions of infinite Consciousness
the negative to that is nothing as as I
said Consciousness is there with the
appearance which means Whenever there is
appearance there is presence of that
which has appeared which is what
appearance is which means there is
consciousness the Infinity of the
Consciousness is the nature of that
appearance the nature of the presence of
the appearance which means Whenever there is
appearance which means Whenever there is
something that something can also be
nothing as in the possibility of it to
cease to not be and that's what what the
mind discerns then the nothingness the
absence of this current presence as we
said when we open up in um reading the
Su about the village the empty of of
certain things so it's the negative so in this
things so it's the negative so in this
case the the most the most subtle
Infinity of Consciousness that's seen as
a as a as a general peripheral phenomena
um even that can be surmounted because
even that is something although it's
very subtle it's still something and
when there is something it's it's its
possibility is to be nothing as in to
cease to disappear so although there is
the present Consciousness the more
greater perception in terms of the
peripheral development is the perception
of nothing
nothingness so um then he understands
that there is only anxiety left upon
depended upon the perception of the
domain of
nothingness then he goes even further
not attending to perception of the
infinite Consciousness perception of the
the domain of nothingness he attends to
the perception of the domain of the
neither perception nor perception so
even that domain of nothingness is a is
a negative in regard to something which
is in the in that case uh the domain of
the infinite Consciousness and uh so
even that domain of nothingness as
peripheral as it is as negative as it is
as subtle it is it's still
perceived to an extent and now that's
what a monk realizes he realizes that
even such a subtle thing it's still
perceived so in order to go even higher
even more generally even more
peripherally he now needs to surmount
the perception it's not anymore about what's
perception it's not anymore about what's
being perceived now he's going beyond
the fact that there is a perception of
any kind of presences or absences
doesn't matter perception is there and
that's what he's surmounting in his in
his next effort so he develops Clarity
he develops understanding he develops uh
Oneness dependent upon the perception of
the domain of the neither perception or
no
perception so he he starts mounting his
own perception and that's why that's why
that's why even this Su says that he
develops clarity about it which means
it's not some sort of mystical step by-
step entering to some transcendental
States it's understanding of the
fundamental nature structural nature of
presence of things of
phenomena so this is the one by one order of that
so this is the one by one order of that
understanding because the structure is
ordered there is a particular thing then
there is more General more General more
General up to the point of surmounting
the Consciousness surmounting the
nothingness surmounting the neither
perception or no
perception so whenever the Buddha spoke
about this in the past about the very
SAS and brah developed this it's not
that they had some some some some
mystical experience that they would
amount to this no they actually
developed the understanding of the
phenomena that's why when the Buddha
became an Arun when became enlightened
when uh when uh when he was encouraged
by the by the Brahma to to go and teach
when he he he begged him to do so
because people might benefit from it the
first person he wanted to go back and
teach was his previous teacher who was
teaching the basis of neither perception
nor perception um and the Buddha wasn't
doing that out of some sort of gratitude
he was doing because that person would
have need absolutely minimal amount of
instruction why because you could see
how far has his mind been developed
beforehand he has developed the
understanding of the phenomena
surpassing the Consciousness the
Infinite Space surpassing the nature of
perception which means he had very very
little dust in his eyes as the Buddha
said and that's why I wanted to go and
teach him but as it turns out he died
beforehand with and and you could could
understand and why it was such a it
would have said oh it's his great loss
cuz he would have understood D in a
finger snap cuz he already done all the
work so so Once the mind gets
established upon the domain of neither
perception or no
perception um then the monk will
understand that there is only that level
of disturbance left which means it is
virtually almost nothing but there is
still more to go um following that
structural development of the of the
peripheral domain um they could not
attend into the perception of domain of
nothingness not attend into perception
of domain of neither perception nor
perception attend to the Oneness
dependent on the signless composure of
the mind so that's where we're even
perceiving the neither perception or no
perception has
ceased so it's really uh well there is
no room for movement there for the
movement of the mind for the movement of
the perception his mind jumps onto it is
perception his mind jumps onto it is
clear about remains with inclines to the
signless composure of the
mind and he understands that there is
only disturbance left to that
extent once he once he fully
um furthermore underu not attending to
the perception of domain of nothingness
not attending to the perception of the
domain of neither perception nor
perception attends to the Oneness
dependent on the signless composure of
the mind his mind jumps onto it's clear
about remains with inclines towards the
signless composure of the mind and then
he understands thus this signless
composure of the mind is determined it
is
intended he understands whatever is
determined that is it is impermanent and
subject to sensation which means that
uh this monk was already at least a s
because uh understanding that Saras are
impermanent it's pretty much the Insight
of of anaria savaka so in order to
to of course that doesn't mean that the
Mind cannot be developed by someone
who's not in Aras savaka but surmounting
neither perception nor perception that
is reserved only for an aria savaka only
for somebody with a Right View because
um as as it became obvious there is no
perception there in a sense of
the mind has been unified surmounting
the nature
perception um but the understanding of
that uh of that place can take uh can
take um sorry the understanding of that
establishment can take place
reflexively whereby when the when the
mind um has developed that Clarity the
mind could realize well as clear as this
is as subtle as this is it is still
determined it's determined by the
perception by the domain of perception
which in itself is determined by the
domain of infinite Consciousness which
in itself is determined by the domain of
the Infinite Space which in itself is
determined by the domain of uh the Earth
which in itself is determined by the
domain of any more um any further
particular perception such as perception
of the forest perception of the village
and so on so he understands whatever is
determined as such it is impermanent so
he penetrates that state with
wisdom and that's that's how there is
absolutely no room in that structure of
the Aris Arisen phenomena Arisen
experience as a whole there is
absolutely no room that hasn't been that
hasn't been pervaded with that
understanding because he surmounted
everything and then what's
left surmounted even that through his
own understanding so there's absolutely
um there's absolutely nothing
left and it says knowing this seeing
this for him the mind is liberated from
the taint of sensuality from the taint
of being from the taint of ignorance the
absolutely nowhere for those things to
to remain hidden on the on the things
that haven't been
upturned um when it is liberated there
is knowledge it is liberated birth is
destroyed holy life has been lived what
should be done has been done so again I
don't think it hurts to repeat this it's
this these are not some transcendental
meditative experiences they're
meditative in a sense of their reflexive
the Mind develops Clarity in regard to
the nature of the present perception and
you could see that even even the very
beginning it was about the
negative when the Buddha was in mig's
mother Palace he wasn't saying look at
this palace look at the floor look at
the post no he was talking about things
that are not
there so from there you go
higher then you realize okay there
things that are there that's where the
mind is established upon but then you go
further so what else is there well that
place is in the forest so the mind can
be established upon the forest even
without you having to go and stare at
the trees and mossy rocks and so
on then what else is there based on
things that are not there so the
understanding of the peripheral and
that's the definition of proper
mindfulness uh where what where by what
you are attending you discern the
peripheral in regard to it and the
ultimate peripheral is the presence of
the phenomenon the infinite
Consciousness then even the greater
peripheral than that it would be even
that place of neither perception or no
perception but that's that's that's now
you bringing it back onto yourself so to
so to develop the full understanding and
then when even that perception ceases in
the signless establishment of the mind
no more signs means no more peripheral
means you have reached the ultimate
peripheral signless cuz all the signs are
signless cuz all the signs are
peripherally that's that's just how the
nature of a sign works so Once the mind
has reached that complete sensation as
in there is no further to go in that
structure and that's by the way the
majima 111 where um sarut one by one
when he would think is there higher
there is that from one goes to the other
one to the other one and he fully
penetrates and understands the entire
structure of the experience from the
inside of course you can't step outside
of it and then he understands okay this
is it this is the ultimate there is no
higher than this the the the signless um
understanding the signless establishment
of the
mind so um so in this case the monk has
has fully understood all the all the all
the more General phenomena in regard to
that which is present in front of him
and because of that he is he realizes
that whatever taint Whatever anxiety
whatever disturbance on based on taint
of sensuality taint of being taint of
ignorance cannot arise for him because
he's free from those
taints and then he realized that only
disturbance based upon the six domain
dependent upon this very body um with
life as condition that's any disturbance
he he he still has left and that's the
disturbance for an Arun for as long as
his body is still alive he can that body
can be disturbed but none of that can
cause suffering or bother him anymore so
all the symptoms of aija have
ceased having he understands having
arrived at this perception it is empty
of the taint of being empty of T of
sensuality taint of being and taint of
ignorance he understands there is only
this non-emptiness namely the six
domains dependent on this very body with
life as condition
thus on account of whatever is not there
he sees it as it is empty and whatever
remains he understand it this is present
and in this wayand there is this
authentic undistorted clear entry into
the emptiness which is the best with
nothing
higher Anand whatever aans and brahmans
in the past entered upon and dwelled in
the clear emptiness which is the best
with nothing higher all of them enter
upon and dwell in this very clear
emptiness which is the best with nothing
higher as that's what I mean it's
structural means The Human Experience
the experience of the five Aggregates
for that matter has certain order and
this is the order that one the one with
understanding develops and understands
so that's why the Buddha says Whoever
has done this in the past ions ago and
whoever will do it in the future will do
it in this manner it's the structure
it's it's not it's not a matter of
choice with nothing higher all of them
enter upon and dwell in this very clear
emptiness which is the best and un
whatever a setting the brah is in the
future will enter upon and dwell in the
clear emptiness which is the best all of
them will enter upon in this very clear
emptiness and same goes for the ones
that do it right now therefore Ananda
you should train yourself thus I will
enter upon and dwell in the clear
emptiness which is the best with nothing
higher this is what the blessed one said
please the venerable an delighted in the
words of the blessed one
so in terms of practical practical
development of um what's been discussed
in the
suta uh physical seclusion is necessary
obviously absence of other people
absence of the perceptions of the
village so ideally places like like
forests mountains where where where uh
where you would be actually physically
removed from other people and then you
don't as I said as I said during the
during the reading you don't have to go
around looking at things and telling
yourself you're in the forest because
you are in the
forest so peripherally you will be
Discerning things that are
absent until then the Mind settles in
the perceptions of the forest the mood
of the experience of the forest and the
only way to develop a mood of the
experience of the forest is to go and be
in the forest or be
alone but there has to be some distance
between between you and other people at
least temporarily for the duration of
that of that
practice so um the perceptions of the
forest are in the
background the tree in front of you the
big rock in front of you the cave next
to you those things are not the forest
they're in the forest and you're there
with them so you are in the forest so as
I said you don't need to keep uh keep
reminding yourself
and and looking at various objects in
front of you and and touching touching
moving looking touching whatever they're
there and you are in that Forest
together with them so you discern the
presence of the forest
peripherally being properly mindful of
it you discern it as something that that
that you partake in you are now in that
Forest you are partaking in that more
General perception and that's how the
mind gets established upon that and you
would see the difference just to spend
two or three days secluded from people
going back among people going back into
the village uh or a
town you will see the difference you
will see how different it is how
different the situation becomes but the
point here is to uh
maintain your uh establishment of Your
Mind through that Clarity of discernment
uh maintain it upon the forest in other
words say you have to go to the town or
the village and um but you even when you
do even when you in the middle of the T
Town Square you still see yourself as
belonging to the forest as belonging to
the greater perception than all these
things that are around you that are
obviously uh more inferior to it
Villages are inferior to the forests
inhabited areas are inferior to the non-
inhabited areas so you see yourself
pertaining partaking in being part of
the greater forest and for as long as
you maintain that
mood peripherally you're mindful of it you
peripherally you're mindful of it you
allow it to endure you can spend long
time among
people and in the towns and Villages and
still partake to the
forest but of course if you see yourself
as partaking to the forest you would
want to be lingering around the
inhabited areas unless you have to so
you would go when you have to do things
that you have to but then go back to
that which is greater the perception of
the forest that is empty of those things
so even when you would be among those
things you're dwelling in The Emptiness
of those things because the mind is
established upon a more General mood and
then say when you get used to dwelling
in the forest when you see yourself
partaking in the forest being part of
the forest go even higher start
Discerning the presence of the
phenomenon of Earth but
perally within which the forest is
within which you
are so now wherever you are whether it's
a forest Town Mountain Island doesn't
matter you are within the perception of
the earth so you could see um say the
perception of the forest upon which your
mood depends upon which your situation
has been developed say there's a massive
flood earthquake fire everything gets
destroyed that's what it means
disturbance upon the perception of the
the forest can still arise but unless
something destroys the entire planet
Earth uh the mind that's established
upon the general perception of the earth
cannot be disturbed then by anything and
that's that's the similar to the
practice of Earth
Casina where the mind gets established
upon it and then would have said
everything inferior to it will not
bother you but the only way to establish this
you but the only way to establish this
is to start Discerning it on the level
of that of the level of that which is
present and that's what the what what
the suit that we just read said said he
understands this is what's
present this is present in front of
me so the peripheral the peripheral um
the peripheral mindfulness of the mood
in the forest is what's present it's
what's my
situation then the peripheral uh the the
Mind established upon the peripheral uh
discernment of the uh of the of the
domain of the perception of the earth is
what my situation is in and then you can
go further to the Infinite Space uh the
infinite Consciousness and so on but
even even just the perception of the
earth is more than enough in terms of
its generality in terms of its its its
its structural capacity to to um to
allow the understanding and The
Sensation of any agreed diversion
delusion lust towards things that are
inferior to it but one needs to start
dwelling in it it's not it's not it's
not a theory it's not an abstract
thought you need to see yourself
partaking you need to see yourself in
your being as something that partakes to
that level of that General perception
that's why he is he's clear about he's
established on it he remains in it he
dwells in
it so that takes repetitive effort and
obviously it takes uh requires
seclusion that's why the Buddha could
not have sort of um encourage too much
monks and those interested in practice
to to go and and develop
physical dwell in physical seclusion
because it all comes from it and there
is that another Sut similar on emptiness
where the man goes into the empty Forest
root of a tree empty cave empty dwelling
and says this place is empty of
others and that's his starting point
again to go back uh into Discerning one
by one this structure of the Arisen
situation of that which is present which
is just another way of saying the
establishment of the mind and janas
working the same way just they they're
more specific in terms of the domain of
sensuality being surmounted and so on
and maybe we can talk about it on
different occasion but in this case um
physical seclusion uh dwelling in that which is
seclusion uh dwelling in that which is
superior to the inhabited life inhabited
areas crowded areas that's how that's
how these
perceptions um begin to be discerned
peripherally and that's how the mind can
get established upon
them so just one more thing to point out
that um the more General perception of
Earth is established upon or rather
through the perceptions of the mood of
the forest the mood of the situation of
being in the
forest uh anything that doesn't go in
that order like one after the other as
in the perception of Earth after the
perception of the mood of the forest it
will be abstract so if it doesn't follow
the right order it's going to be on the
level of abstraction abstraction which
means there won't be mindfulness
properly established and mind will not
be established upon that uh one
pointedness uh of that more General
perception so if if a person wants to
discern the perceptions of Earth they
need to be done within or on the basis
or through the basis of the of the mood
of being in the forest the mood of being
part of the forest the mood of being the
forest within that then you start
refining that very mood perception of
the mood of being the forest and that's
where the perception of Earth is found